this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software for software engineering radio
am Elena Salinas Pete Kumon is the
co-founder and CTO of Optimizely after
earning his master's degree in computer
science from the University of Illinois
at urbana-champaign Pete joined Google
as a product manager where he helped
launch and grow Google App Engine to
more than 150,000 developers in 2009
Pete teamed up with dan Soroka to star
their first company carrot sticks an
online math game for kids less than a
year later Pete and then created
Optimizely during the Y Combinator
winter 2010 class Optimizely is an
experimentation platform that allows
marketing and product teams to test
learn and deploy digital experiences
Pete is co-author of AV testing the most
powerful way to turn clicks into
customers today we're gonna talk about
a/b testing and how to implement it Pete
welcome to software engineering radio
thank you very much' Dana let's begin
with what a/b testing is can you
describe what this means sure so a B
testing is a way to run experiments to
make your marketing and product design
better so the concept is really simple
it's been around for a long time we
didn't invent this but let's imagine you
have a website and you are using that
website to let's say solicit donations
for a political campaign for example a B
testing is this idea that you can take
any individual element on that website
and try several different variations
right maybe you've got three different
headlines and you want to understand
which of those resonates most with
potential donors and so each time
somebody visits your website you show
them one of those random
and then over time once you've collected
enough data you measure which one
actually got more people to donate in
that example
that's an a/b test so you mentioned it's
a way to run experiments and the main
objective is to make this product better
and if I'm understanding this correctly
you're showing different variations and
then based on some metrics that you see
you decide let's go with variation B
100% that's right so every every
experiment in you know in in the field
of Technology a/b testing as well as in
science you know starts with a
hypothesis right
your hypothesis might be I think if I
change this headline then I'm going to
increase my donations by 5% for example
and a/b testing is a way to test that
you know collect it collect objective
data and making the decision based on
data and evidence rather than you know
the highest paid person's opinion for
example which I think is how a lot of
decisions get made yeah yeah that makes
a lot of sense you mentioned you didn't
invent a B testing it's been around what
I read is that it used to be more
difficult due to lack of suitable
tooling can you explain what engineers
needed to do before to set up an a/b
test
so I mentioned a/b testing been around
for a long time it really been around
for a long time so you can actually go
back and read about experiments that
were run in the mail-order catalog days
so companies like Sears would create
different versions of their made allured
and catalog and send them out and then
measure you know the number of orders
they got from each of those versions and
so this idea has been around for for a
long long time our founding insight for
the company optimized who was that this
was a very powerful technique which had
been adopted at large scale at companies
like Google and Amazon but was a lot
less common outside of kind of the high
technology companies we believe because
it was so difficult to do and so it used
to be that you needed a you know a team
of software engineers to run any
give an experiment and so what we saw
even at even at Google where the
practice was relatively common what we
saw was marketing teams wanting to run a
whole bunch of experiments and
engineering teams basically not caring
right and and being focused on their own
roadmap and that every experiment that
you wanted to run required kind of
getting onto the backlog in the
engineering team and and that friction
meant that companies were just
experimenting a lot less and so our
original insight was that you know if
you make it easier companies will run
more experiments they'll make better
decisions overall so we built a product
that gave our customers a kind of a
WYSIWYG visual editor that allowed them
to go in and change images and change
headlines and do all of this without
needing to depend on a team of software
engineers to do it so that was it was
our first product was really a product
focused on non technical or semi
technical marketers who wanted to run
experiments on their websites so it's
been it's been nine years since we
started the company we've expanded an
awful lot we've we now have a product
called full stack which is targeted much
more product development teams and
software engineers to run experiments in
their products we've got a whole range
of tools we offer and our goal now is
really to help large companies build and
scale their experimentation programs I
see and to understand this a little bit
more and for those that aren't very
familiar with it it sounds like what
you're doing at Optimizely is you found
this way to generalize how to create an
a/b test and implemented and before it
was more of each company had to do this
in-house and it might not be their
priority they have to build features and
things like that but if we were talking
about those early days for example if I
have the website that you mentioned for
donations you know I want to test two
different images how would I just go
about doing it would I would I be adding
conditionals to my website or have two
different endpoints what are some
other things involved sure so the we
actually there were a couple tools out
there ready-made tools for a/b testing
before we started but both of them
required a lot more technical work in
order to build an experiment and so you
would be you know in the case of a
website you'd be tagging you'd have to
go in and tag some of the different HTML
elements to signify to the you know the
client library which variation each
element belonged in and so anytime you
wanted to run an experiment you had to
go in and retag your website and so that
that alone required the help of you know
the software engineering team and if we
I mean I don't know how technical we
want to get so please feel free to stop
me but one of the insights that we had
was that we that you could accomplish
this you could build an a/b test and
execute an a/b test without needing to
touch your website code at all in the
way that we did this was we gave folks
as I mentioned a visual editor and that
would allow them to design an experiment
which we would then encode as a series
of JavaScript statements and those
JavaScript statements were compiled into
a client library which would update that
library the contents of that library
would update every time a customer
changed their experiment and so what
that meant was that we would update this
client library so that the customer
didn't need to update their website and
they would include this single line
include on the page and then our code
would execute changes to the Dom as the
page was loading and that's how we were
able to get around this requirement for
an engineering team to go in and make a
bunch of changes every time you wanted
to start or stop an experiment mm-hmm
yes I see earlier you are talking about
starting with the hypotheses in terms of
a be testing in your book maybe testing
the most powerful way to turn clicks
into customers I think I saw there's a
section of lessons learned from 200,000
AP tests and Counting and here you talk
about different steps to go about
starting doing a/b testing and defining
this and you mentioned earlier the hype
the C's in step 1 you talk about define
success can you give some examples of
what success can mean you know based on
previous experiments yeah
so I think one of the biggest lessons
that I have learned is that a B tests
experimentation is not just a matter of
throwing a bunch of stuff at a wall and
seeing what sticks and I think it's a
shame because that is often how its
portrayed
but I think organizations that do this
really well one of the things they do is
they're really rigorous about coming up
with well-qualified hypotheses to
experiment on and a hypotheses is is
really just a guess it's usually an
informed guess that some particular
change will result in some outcome and
that outcome is the idea that you know
that's that's your definition of success
and so if we go back to our example
before of you know I'm running an
organization and using a website to
collect donations right the the success
metric might be the number of donations
I'm able to collect right or it might be
the number of emails that I've added to
my you know my retargeting list every
experiment may have a slightly different
definition of success every organization
right has a different definition of
success but it's really important before
you start going out and testing things
to align with your organization what
does success mean for us right and then
how do we measure that I see and even in
this area you just mentioned it's not
good to just be throwing a lot of stuff
out there and see what works and I guess
that's easy now with with all these
tooling you can just be having a lot of
versions out there what are some of the
disadvantages of going by this approach
of just constantly releasing you know
some tweak in the UI or in the workflow
and what impact can then have sure so I
mean any change you make anything you've
build or do takes effort and time and
attention right and there's only a fixed
amount of all of those things on any
and so you there is a need to balance
right the the desire to test everything
in experiments on everything right
because you are you're drawing on finite
resources when you do that you know
that's that's one side and then the
other side is that in general any
decision that you make with the benefit
of data is going to be a better decision
and so these two forces are kind of
coming up against each other and that's
why I think it's so important to
emphasize a need for a well qualified
hypothesis right it's not you know I see
sometimes every once in a while though
it's less common stories about changing
a button from you know red to red to
blue or whatever and it in resulting in
some gain and I generally think those
are garbage you know I I think I suspect
most of them are statistical noise and
you know worse than that though they're
not informative they don't teach you
anything and they they're often not
based on any sound insight so you know
going back to this there's an infinite
set of things that anybody could
experiment I'm the thing that you used
to narrow that down is something
meaningful is your understanding of your
customer your design sense all of those
things that go into making every other
business decision still important in
this context I seen since we're talking
about step number one which is defining
success you mentioned just a quick recap
some of the metrics for success are
specific to your product right like the
number of donations the number of
signups to your newsletter or something
like that is there any other metric that
that you can think of oh sure I mean so
we've built our product in a pretty
general way and we we try to make it as
easy as possible for our customers to
measure whatever metric it is that is
important to them and that might be you
know donations or emails collected as I
mentioned in that example it could be
ecommerce revenue it could be traffic to
a particular page it could be clicks on
a headline so it really really depends
on the situation okay step number two in
these lessons learned from running a lot
of a/b tests involves identifying
bottlenecks
what do you mean by this well I think
with any time you're building anything
right there's a we come to this back to
this idea of needing to focus and
prioritize your time and so you can ask
this question you know I've got I've got
this big website maybe I'm just starting
to experiment where should I start
right you know and the idea here is pick
the area where there's the lowest
hanging fruit there's the you know the
biggest opportunity to make a an
improvement and one way to find that is
just by looking at your analytics right
look and and see where your users are
dropping out of your funnel and chances
are the places where there are the
biggest drop-offs there's also the
biggest opportunity to make some
improvement so if you see that you're
getting you know you're getting great
conversion rates on your your your
Google campaigns and you're getting tons
of traffic but then most people aren't
getting beyond your landing page there's
a good chance that your landing page
isn't resonating with your audience you
know and experimentation is one great
way of starting to figure out you know
how do I fix this how to make it better
so it's in the end of the day it's it's
really it's a way to learn about your
audience and rate every everything
that's suboptimal about your business
suggests there's something you don't
fully understand about your customer and
a be testing is nothing other than a way
to try alternatives so that you can
build that understanding I see so like
you're highlighting the main thing in
a/b testing is understanding your users
and by this you should have metrics in
place on your website or on your product
that can give you the insight of why
aren't they clicking that final pay
button in the donation website right
yeah it's it's or
I think it's I honestly think it's it's
hard to often arrive at real customer
insights using analytics right analytics
I think is really great at telling you
where the problems are I don't think
it's very good at telling you why those
problems exist or how to solve them and
that's really where experimentation
comes in what is a role of user studies
and focus
in a bee testing those are both really
valuable tools I think there's you know
I certainly think that a bee you can't a
bee test your way from a blank page to a
successful business and there are many
many many things you have to do right to
build anything successful you know we
know anyway that you can sit down in
front of your customers and learn more
about them is going to be extremely
valuable and the two that you just
mentioned are great ones I actually went
often when speaking with early-stage
entrepreneurs I will advise them not to
run a bee test right a bee tests are a
relatively sophisticated way and even
with our software which i think is
fantastic still a fairly high effort way
of getting the gains the gains I think
are you know well worth it but if you
only have a couple hundred users on your
website or your app every month there's
not a lot of benefit in going through
the work involved in it I think as an
early-stage entrepreneur for example
you're much better off going out and
finding 10 people who love your product
and figuring out why they love it you
know or 10 people who hate your product
figure out why they hate it that kind of
in-person interaction is is really high
bandwidth and maybe a better use of the
small customer base you have I seen your
mentioning if your have few users just
doing in-person tests or something like
that is a be testing the answer to
scaling those user studies and focus
groups in a way I absolutely think it is
right a focus group for example is a
it's a high bandwidth way of getting
information out of a small and not
necessarily representative sample right
so you pick you know five people and go
and talk to them and you're going to get
a lot of information during that
interaction but those five people don't
necessarily represent you know how your
broader audience is going to behave and
a be testing is just a way of taking
advantage of the fact that you have
hundreds of thousands or millions of
users out there and that you can observe
directly how they're responding to your
changes so that you can provide them the
best experience possible step number
three is constructing a hypotheses which
we talked about earlier the next step is
prioritize you mentioned also
is briefly at the beginning can you talk
in more detail what prioritization and
compasses in a/b testing sure so this is
a hard problem like it is for in any
domain in a in a large organization and
as I mentioned before we're again coming
back to this problem that there's
there's like a billion things you can
test at any given point right there's
always more ideas and there is capacity
to execute on them in any context and
prioritization is as important in
experimentation as it is in product
development or marketing campaigns or
anything else and so some great ways to
do that are aligning with your
organization again on what are those
success metrics right so if we decide of
all of the things we could possibly
measure these are the few numbers that
we really care about the most that's one
way to really force prioritization and
then sitting down coming up with a
backlog of experiments ranking them for
example by expected impact on those
metrics and then using you maybe a
series of open meetings and discussions
to get the whole organization aligned on
the the the roadmap for experimentation
and we've seen it at really
sophisticated organizations this process
is really merged tightly with actually
the product backlog process right and
and that's because it is it becomes kind
of it becomes unheard of to launch
something especially something big
without running some kind of experiment
and so you see at these more
sophisticated organizations their
experiment backlogged really is their
product backlog and their experiment
prioritization process is the same as
their product prioritization process
what would you say are the groups in the
organization involved in this
prioritization it sounds like there's
engineers but also maybe people in
marketing or managers product managers
so we have seen experimentation really
transformed the way both marketing teams
and product teams go about their work
and I think it's true that any team that
works on some some thing some digital
experience can benefit from this and so
I talked about these use cases as though
they're separate because sometimes they
are right you may have a team of
marketers that's responsible for
you know the promotions on a landing
page and then a separate team of
engineers and product managers who are
responsible for building a product that
you're selling those at the end of the
day are both digital experiments sorry
digital experiments experiences and they
can both benefit from experimentation
the next step is about the test itself
we talked about how is not recommended
to just be throwing out there a lot of
tests because real customers are seeing
these different variations and there
could be confusion of the product if it
keeps changing constantly if we assume
we have a set of few tests that we are
trying out how do we decide when to
finish running these tests that's a
really good question so first I want to
mention I actually don't think it's a
bad thing to run a lot of tests I think
it's a really good thing to run a lot of
tests what I think is bad is
undisciplined testing or test that
experiments that don't have a reason for
running right and this back to this idea
of using well-qualified hypotheses to
decide which experiments you run and
which ones you don't I think most most
websites run by large companies
especially are changing constantly and
users have kind of come to expect that
so it's it's less a question of maybe
too much change for user and more
question of making sure that as an
organization you're focused on things
are gonna have an impact so that's
that's one but your question was about
how long you run an experiment and this
is a really this is a question that we
have spent a lot of time thinking about
it actually there there are some things
in that book that I think are are not
correct right this was written in 2013
and we were a relatively young
organization and I think there were some
things that we that we didn't really
understand or get right even at the time
and one of the biggest areas where I
think we made some mistakes here was in
how we thought about and how we talked
about statistics and specifically how
you decide how long to run an experiment
and whether or not you you know can draw
some conclusion from it and so I'll tell
a story about this so the kind of a
standard technique in the field and and
well outside of just a/b testing it's
it's widely used in the sciences as well
is something called a t-test it's a
fixed horizon
to deciding how long during an
experiment and the reason is called
fixed horizon is because you actually
make the decision for how long to run
the experiment before you started the
experiment and so this involves making
essentially a prediction about the
impact that experiments gonna have so
you say well I predict this is going to
have a you know three percent impact on
on this particular metric and so then
given that that that the size of the
effect that you want to detect you then
compute how many data points you need to
make to draw a conclusion from that and
then you run the experiment for that
long and that's the that is the correct
approach to using a t-test the challenge
is that a lot of people who run
experiments these days don't have a
formal statistics background and they're
used to getting analytics and data in
real time and so the idea that you ought
to sort of make this prediction and then
come up with a fixed length to run an
experiment before you've collected any
data is very counterintuitive and that's
dangerous because if you use the t-test
but you don't follow those rules then
you actually are going to get a much
higher error rate than you think you're
going to and that's one of the mistakes
we made in that book in particular was
in not describing correctly how to use
that t-test and so this was something
that that you know me personally and a
lot of folks that optimizes he lost a
lot of sleep over and what we ended up
deciding was that the t-test so this
standard accepted technique was actually
not really appropriate for use in a
digital context unless you had a lot of
expertise in how to use it in a lot of
discipline and so what we ended up doing
was we launched something in I think
early 2015 that we call stats engine and
that takes some more recent techniques
and by recent I mean from the last maybe
50 years versus the last hundred years
take some more recent techniques and
uses them to come up with a analysis
tools that allow our customers to check
their results all the way through an
experiment and make a decision as soon
as as soon as excuse me they have enough
data to call a result significant so we
try to we try to build an approach here
that conforms more to the way
users are used to working these days
rather than trying to change our
customers behavior so with the way this
work is that they're constantly seeing
the results and if they don't see they
they keep changing they can call it a
conclusion or something is that how it
works yeah so the the way that you can
look at the data our results report
works as you can see in real-time how
your different variations and your
experiments are performing and on in
addition to that right you might see
like I've got three variations and this
one has a conversion rate of 3% and this
one has a conversion rate of 4% and this
one has a you know conversion rate of 5%
in addition to seeing those that the
performance numbers are the point
estimates you can also see a set of
statistical recommendations and that's
in the form of error bars that try to
give you an indication of the range
where the true conversion rate lives as
well as a number we call statistical
significance and that statistical
significance number will change in real
time right as you collect more data but
once that crosses a certain threshold
our users are ok to stop the experiment
and draw a conclusion and that's the
that's really where the fundamental
differences between our approach and the
more traditional approach is that using
a more traditional approach you can
still calculate the significance numbers
in real time and they're still going to
fluctuate but you're not allowed to use
them to draw a conclusion until you've
reached that predetermined sample size
and that's where most people get it
wrong I see let's talk about what
happens after we finish doing an a/b
test for example in in what ways are
these results used for maybe further
testing and things like that are they
used for that so I think ideally they
write a good a B test ought to you know
create more questions than it does
answers right because you've ideally
you've taken some hypotheses and you've
either confirmed or denied that hype or
invalidated that hypothesis and that
arleigh due to a new set of questions
like oh well if this worked what else
will work you know what did we learn
that helps inform maybe what we can do
even better and if this didn't work what
was wrong about our understanding right
so back to that example of a you know
trying to collect camp donations to
political campaign maybe you tried a set
of headlines maybe you tried a headline
that you thought would resonate with
voters and maybe you've got you saw no
significant difference or you know at
worse maybe maybe it actually made
things worse so why did that happen and
how can you take that learning that you
just got and use it to improve the
experience even more since we've been
talking about this donation example for
a lot in this episode where you the one
that that worked on this and fourth was
it for the Obama campaign no so I can
talk a bit about the history of the
company so my co-founder and I started
the company in 2010 and the real
inspiration for that you know the
customer problem that we tried to solve
actually came from my co-founders
experience on the the the Obama campaign
in 2008 so he and I met at Google he
left Google in late oh seven and joined
the Obama campaign and it was there that
he took this technique which was used
commonly at Google and applied it in to
a presidential campaign where it was
really relatively unknown and it was it
had a big impact on the the amount of
donations they collected online and the
campaign broke a lot of Records there
but it was also is kind of one of those
things where I think what he took away
from that was how this was really
powerful but it sure was difficult to do
I wonder if we can make it easier and
that's where our inspiration came from
for this company exactly and like you
said both you and your co-founder had
use this technique at Google and a lot
of these things start at big companies
but then the small companies don't have
the resources to be doing this so that's
why it's important you know to have
companies like optimizes that are making
this techniques available to different
kinds of products right that was that
was our thesis right and that's that's
certainly how we got our start I would
say today we spend more time working
with some of the largest organizations
right we work with 26 out of the Fortune
100 and I think I think there's
something to me like maybe
experimentation is hard right and that's
that was that was the thesis we had when
we started the company and I
or experience over the last nine years
has only confirmed that it's difficult
when we started we were mostly focused
on some of the technical challenges
involved in running an experiment right
we built this visual editor this single
line install we made a lot of these
hurdles smaller I think what we've
learned over time is that there are just
as many if not more organizational
hurdles that a company has to go through
to do this some of these questions about
how you prioritize you know like that
what kind of team you need to build in
order to do this in order to run the
experiments or analyze them these are
all difficult thorny questions that big
companies have just as much trouble
answering and so our goal now is when we
when we work with the companies not just
to provide software is to provide
software services knowledge and
understanding and how to build this into
your culture exactly and it's
interesting that you bring that up
because I sometimes see headlights on
the headlines on the news describing how
users complain about a change in the
product I think there was one in an
Instagram recently where they made
horizontal scrolling and it was just an
experiment released by mistake to the
the real users a very broad set of them
can you talk a bit about this like
determining who to release it to a test
you're not gonna release it to to like
have my users and the other half are
gonna see this right yes so that can be
sometimes a real challenge and I loved
your point about changes in a product
kind of resulting in frustration amongst
users because I think there's there's
just several really good examples over
the last five years of companies that
have maybe skipped the process of
experimentation and gathering real user
feedback and have rolled out broadly
changes that ended up having a hugely
negative impact on their business
snapchat comes to mind I think yeah
that's another good point yeah and and
so you know I we've used this example of
collecting donations in a political
campaign but as I mentioned before this
is just as relevant and product
development context right if you're
going to invest months of you know a
software engineering teams time in
building a feature you should
and that that feature is going to be
beneficial to your users in your company
and experimentation is a really good way
to do that so you asked like how do you
determine in that context how who should
see who should see the you know a
particular feature and there's different
ways of doing it the easiest way is just
say you know I'm just gonna carve out
maybe 5% 10% 50% whatever it is and show
it to them sometimes it's not always
that easy and there's interesting cases
where where you actually you can't just
be as naive about that so another you
know may be a classic case where this is
where this is the case is testing with
price you know it's this can be very
sensitive thing is showing one price to
one user another price to other users in
some context it can even be illegal and
so these are all things you have to take
into account there's other interesting
thing interesting complications that
come in when you've got a you know a
business with large network effects so
you know I've spoken a lot to the team
at Airbnb for example they run a ton of
experiments and some of the things they
have to take into account are you know
if they run a big experiment on a set of
hosts
then there yeah if they run a big
experiment on a set of hosts then that
the the changes they make to those set
of hosts may impact the users the end
users are so they I guess the guests the
guests behavior and those guests then
may be interacting with some hosts that
are in the treatment and some hosts that
are not in the treatment and so you get
these you can no longer assume that all
of your data points are independent
which then throws your results into
question so they have to spend a lot of
time actually designing their - their
sample groups you know taking this into
into account so I've seen some some
organizations solve this problem by for
example isolating only particular cities
to expose things to you know our
particular markets where you can be
relatively sure that changes you make
within that market may have effects
within that market but aren't going to
you know if you make a change to your
your product that only folks on the East
Coast see you may may have less of a
chance of impacting the behavior on the
west coast and so you isolate your
changes that way so there's a whole kind
of science behind
you how you best pick a sample group
okay
let's go back a little bit to this the
way in which a be testing can be used in
products like you mentioned some
companies release a major design without
having run you know shorter experiments
about it we can test a major redesign at
scale I guess before we build it because
then we already invested resources in
building it how can we justify investing
resources in a major redesign that we
later find bit worse that's a good well
a lot of companies seem to do it so I
you know there must be okay but so how
can you how can you justify spending
resources on a major redesign that may
make the experiments experience worse
for users there's a couple approaches
you can take to mitigate risk and a lot
of I think testing in a product context
is about risk mitigation it's about
making sure that the effort you spend on
your product actually results in an
improvement and one approach that we've
seen are is something called a painted
door test where it's called painted door
after you know the old Looney Tunes
cartoons where you know that someone
would paint a door on a rock and it
looks like a door but it's actually you
know it's a classic example of this is
is you know you just put a link for like
try this new feature and then when the
user clicks on it it says okay coming
soon you know let us know if you're
interested in this where it's a really
low effort way to gauge whether there's
demand for something that you're
thinking about building you can test
smaller sub components so if you're
doing a major redesign take some smaller
components and test those first right
maybe that may be in areas where it's
it's you know gonna be a little safer to
do so it'll have less of an impact on
your business and hopefully you can do
that in a way that where you kind of
front-load the experiments so that you
can decide you know if you know should
you continue the project or should you
make changes to it but in the in the
worst case it's you know if let's say
it's something that you truly can't
experiment on until after you've
invested months or years of effort into
doing it I still think it's worth
running that experiment because the
alternative is is potentially something
that looks like what snapchat ended up
doing which was to launch a major set of
changes without having run that run
those experiments and it's had a huge
impact on their business and so even if
you've invested all at that time and and
the that you know wouldn't you want to
know the impact was going to be negative
before you rolled it out it still would
have been better to say okay nuts to
this we're gonna do something else than
it was to roll it out in my view so
saying is definitely doable if we
dissect the major design idea and we can
test some components or at like sneak
peeks I think there are ways to
front-load the your experimentation to
try and try and reduce risk upfront
absolutely I mean user groups like the
the menu user studies folks who those
are another way of collecting that kind
of data early on and at the end of the
day all of this is really again about
learning about your customers and as a
product manager you ought to be making
every attempt to do that before you
invest effort like this let's talk a bit
more about implementing a be testing for
example there are different ways that
you can go about doing it we first
talked about the old way where it's
in-house you have dedicated engineers
you can also hire somebody to do the
testing for you I'm thinking you hire a
different company to do it you can build
your own tool you can buy an existing
tool what do you recommend for
organizations that are just starting to
explore it
this idea of a be testing for an
organization is really just starting to
explore it I think the implementation at
that point is is less important than
starting to build some cultural momentum
around it and so there's we've seen many
examples where experiment a program an
experimentation program inside an
organization will start because some
team has run some experiment that ends
up being really successful and and ends
up you know changing the course of the
product direction or you know giving
giving some big yield right and that
example ends up getting enough attention
internally that there's a lot of
interest that grows around it
and something like that is usually
necessary in order to start building
support for investing larger resources
in building a larger program and so I
actually think you're right that there
you know you can use something like
optimize that you can use there you know
a number of competitors of ours offer
products there are some open source
invitations you can even build your own
although it's something that usually
takes a lot more effort yeah I wouldn't
recommend if you're just dipping your
toe into the water but the important
thing is you find meaningful experiments
to run that end up setting a great
example for the rest of your
organization because that's what really
builds momentum and then once you've
gotten that momentum then you can start
to think okay how do we scale this and
how do we build a program that makes it
easy as easy as possible for many of our
other teams in the company to run those
experiments so a way that I see this
starting is first make sure you already
have metrics from your product and then
start thinking about those numbers and
asking questions like why are we really
seeing sign ups and that kind of stuff
right start having questions that you
you're just trying to figure out what
the answer is that's a really good way
to start any experiment is just what
what are the biggest questions that we
have right I think there's a there's a
great going back to this kind of moment
where experimentation explodes within an
organization there's a really good
example in the early days of uber I
spoke to some some former uber employees
and who told me the story in the early
days of uber they had to make a decision
on launching cash payments in in India
and the team on the ground in India
wanted to accept cash because it's a
it's a you know cash plays a really
important role in that economy still but
management in the u.s. didn't want to do
that and so there was a kind of this
back-and-forth and so the team on the
ground decided to run an experiment they
figured out a kind of low cost way of
building cash payments and they did that
they ran this experiment and they showed
that when you exposed riders to the
option of paying with cash they signed
up at a higher rate and then they
retained at a much higher rate as well
and so the results are really dramatic
and that ended up getting the management
team in the u.s. to change their view
and they ended up long
cash payments in India and elsewhere and
that that example got so much attention
inside the company that that was then
end up being the motivation for building
their own experimentation platform
internally and a team around it yeah
that's around that's a really good story
I didn't know about it I wanna talk now
specifically about Optimizely which is a
platform to do experimentation earlier
you mentioned some of its components can
you give an overview of about what I
like Optimizely looks like can I give an
overview on what a tool like Optimizely
looks like yeah what are some of the
things that you can do sure sure so we
have our product is really broken down
in several parts or kind of our two
flagship products are a product we call
Optimizely web and another one we call
Optimizely full stack and Optimizely web
is built for non-technical and semi
technical users to run experiments on
web pages and that includes this visual
you know WYSIWYG editor that I mentioned
before it's often used by marketing
teams to do things like optimize landing
pages home pages our other product that
I mentioned is called full stack and
that is targeted much more towards
product development teams and software
engineers and so rather than using a
visual editor you are using a set of I
think 11 open-source SDKs which you
embed in your product the idea is you
should be able to run experiments
anywhere that you run code and you can
use the combination of the SDK along
with our web interface to configure a
set of experiments or feature flags that
you then use to to configure how your
product shows up to users and you can
collect data using these experiments you
can turn features on and off you can
slowly ramp them up from 0 to 100% and
all of this is designed to help you use
data and science to to decide how to
develop your products we also have a
product we call program management which
instead of being focused on actually
building and executing experiments helps
organizations plan and manage the
process of running
so you can manage all of the teams that
are running experiments they keep a
backlog of ideas they can stack rank
them and vote on them as an
administrator a program manager you get
a bird's-eye view of everything that's
going on in your organization do we have
to build our applications in our
products to be a be test friendly is
there such a thing that's that's a
really good question so I think that is
something I advise I don't think it's
required right but anything is it as a
product development team that you can do
to make product development easier
whether it's the experimentation or
something else I think is a good idea
and so you know one of the one of the
ways that you can do this I mentioned
before you can use our SDKs to run
experiments inside your products and the
way that that's actually done is using
conditional logic and our our SDK to say
if the users bucketed into variation a
versus variation B show this versus this
we actually expose something that we
call live variables is the name we use
and that is it gives you the ability to
define a set of variables which you can
then using our interface give different
values to in different variations so you
might you know say like number of search
results in variation one should be five
but in variation two should be ten and
one way to make it very easy to to
design and run these experiments is to
separate the configuration of a given
feature from the business logic of that
feature and once you've done that you
can connect that configuration so all of
these kind of variable values that are
important to how the feature runs to a
tool like Optimizely where you can then
once you've done that run an arbitrary
number of experiments on what those
values should be so I used that you know
the example before the number of search
results that appear in a search results
page but you might also use right the
the size of the links you know the you
know the gravity constant in a game
right there's any number of things that
you could then use once you use this
this design pattern to experiment and
and figure out the best configuration
for your product where does the decision
of what variation of a page to serve
happen does this occur on the client
side or on
sir Versailles with with our full-stack
product yeah this this this actually
happens it can it's up to you as a
software engineer so you know you can
use our c-sharp SDK for example or node
SDK to run experiments where the
bucketing decision and that logic
happens on the server side before the
request is served you can also use a an
SDK on the client whether it's a you
know an iPhone or an Android application
or a webpage we offer SDKs for those
environments as well you can use those
to execute a that decision on the client
side as well and so it ends up becoming
more of an architecture decision you can
also use multiple SDKs in concert with
each other they all consume the same
data file and so it's really up to you
to architect your approach in the way
that makes the most sense for a given
experiment are there trade-offs between
the two doing it on the client side
versus on the server side absolutely
so that as with anything on the client
side it involves it involves more
sending more data over the over the wire
in one way or another and that can have
a latency impact specifically with web
pages for example if you are making
changes to the Dom as the page is
loading it's not only a matter of having
to download more data to the users
browser but it's a matter of making
changes using JavaScript as the page is
being rendered which can which has cost
as well you can make those decisions
using full stack on the server side and
that's it's much faster there's there's
you know almost zero latency impact but
in most cases that involves more work as
well right it's often easier within an
organization to make changes to
client-side code that it is server-side
code for a bunch of reasons it seemed
because like you said maybe the it
sounds like if it's in the client side
it can be faster to implement it but it
can have performance impacts on on the
user's usually the trade-off we see and
there's ways to manage that performance
impact but it ultimately comes down to a
question of you know velocity versus
versus latency and and needing to make a
decision in the way that's best for your
users your
yeah because you you might decide oh it
increases the time to load from one
second to one-and-a-half seconds and
maybe you're like I don't think that
will impact our users how they perceive
the product and then we can just finish
this a B test it's exactly right that's
that's exactly what I think about it I
think you know understanding that impact
and then deciding okay is it worth
taking that hit to latency you know for
the next two weeks while we gather
enough data and make a decision or
should we instead our build this on the
on the server side and I mentioned
before I should clarify a velocity
versus latency when I say a velocity in
this context I mean the velocity of your
experimentation right if you the easier
it is to build and run an experiment the
more you can run the faster you can run
them versus versus the latency of the
user experience a B testing is not only
about testing changes in the UI which
we've been talking about throughout this
conversation what our server-side
changes that can be a be tested so I
gave that example before of you know the
number of search results that might
appear on a search results page but the
things that you can test are just vast
right you might test the different
responses in an Alexa app you know or a
chat bot you might test price you know
which is something that's often easier
to do on the server side really any
business logic that you execute on the
server side are things you can
experiment with in full stack and that's
what makes it so powerful can this be
also about a/b testing different
implementations of your IPS for example
if you have you're using c-sharp and
then you're like ah let's just use no to
serve this and is it also in that
concert so that's that's another really
good one is understanding the trade-offs
between two different implementations of
some API it's it's maybe maybe you're
trying to improve your the latency of
your you know query processor and you've
you've you've built a new version and
you want to understand its performance
relative to the old version one way to
do that is just send 10% of queries to
the new version and use an experiment to
measure and write and as you see
promising results then you can increase
the percentage of queries that go to
your your new version and and then
you've got it even even something as
simple as you know making sure that your
code is actually doing what you think it
should be doing right so every feature
has bugs in it inside one way or another
and if you decide to roll out a new
feature to a small percentage of users
you can limit the blast radius of those
of the bugs and that's in it in a way
that's that's just an experiment it's
something you can do with Optimizely you
know or another feature flagging tool
and what scale does a company need to be
operating for it to start doing a/b
tests good question I mean it you know I
don't think there's a concrete answer to
that you do as I mentioned before you
need enough data to be able to make me
you know to make the effort required to
run an experiment worth it and I don't
have a hard and fast number there even I
will suggest that if you have if you
have a if you're just getting started
out like I mentioned before I think
you're probably gonna get a lot more
mileage out of conversations with your
customers right as it it's an
entrepreneur that's something we learned
over and over again but if you if you do
want to run an a/b test and I've seen
good examples of people running good a B
test even a smaller size focus on
changes that you think are gonna have a
big impact right like again this this
sort of nonsense example of you know
testing the blue button first is the
green button I think it's a waste of
time at any size but particularly if
you're a tiny company you don't have
many customers like you know if you're
gonna run an experiment you run it on
something big that you think is gonna
have a big impact because the bigger the
effect the easier it is detect to detect
with less data I see I wanna switch
gears a little bit and talk about some
of the ethical concerns of doing a/b
testing these can arise depending on how
we set up our experiments one example
that I could think of was Facebook's
experiment of showing users more
positive or negative posts where do we
draw the line of what's ethical and a/b
testing or how can we have that
conversation within an organization it's
a really good
and that's that's a question every
organization really anything needs to
ask an answer for themselves because the
the ethical concerns don't stop with an
experiment right they stop anytime
you're building any kind of product that
has an impact on your users lives and
Facebook has has found itself in the
position where they can have a huge
impact on society and they're having to
tap with some of these these questions
now you know I don't I don't know if I
have a hard and fast answer for this
right it's at Optimizely we we spend a
lot of time thinking about our culture
and our values and we're very
intentional about those things we wrote
them down very early and and even today
they play a big part in how we operate
as a business and you know I personally
think is very important to take a
principled stand to what it means to be
a high integrity business a high
integrity company and hopefully if
you've been intentional enough about
your values and if you if you really as
a leadership team set the example living
by them then those decisions become a
bit easier but again this ends up
becoming something that every company
really needs to decide for themselves
yeah the way I see this going adding on
to what you mentioned earlier that the
first step is to have this culture of
testing in the organization I see this
just being yet another component of this
culture of testing like hypotheses and
then we can also have a section of what
it can be you know negative impacts of
this or ethical questions but that's how
I see it going yeah I think you're right
you know it I don't know the details of
the of the Facebook case that you
mentioned but I think it had something
to do with making some changes as you
mentioned that that had a more positive
slant to your newsfeed versus there were
negative slant and you know again I
don't think this is really a question
about the the ethics of experimentation
because these are these are decisions
that Facebook has to make no matter what
and the process of gathering data and
and understanding what that impact is is
something that hopefully will inform a
decision may be the best way for
ensuring that you are running these
kinds of experiments in service of good
is to decide intentionally a friend how
will we use this data to make the best
decision possible for our customers
right if it turns out that you know
making the newsfeed is more negative
results in more engagement but is you
know is it has harmful effects then
that's something that ought to be
discussed long before that we start
collecting that data and we ought to
know okay once we collect this data and
once we understand this the answer to
this question how will we use that to
make a decision about the experiments
because that's that's what really
matters what are some of the steps to
start creating a culture of testing in
an organization what are some of the
steps to start creating a culture of
experimentation like if there's somebody
listening from in a small company or a
medium company and they're like we're
not doing any testing we're just
building stuff and not getting as much
as gay engagement as we could how can
they go about suggesting this or yeah
getting started on one way I mentioned
earlier is just by running good
experiments and talking about them in an
organization I mean that's that's just
the key to building and you know a
curiosity excitement momentum around
this idea but sooner or later you really
need to have a leadership team that is
bought into this yeah if you do that's
great right that's that to me is a
strong sign you've got a good leadership
team in place but one way that leaders
can contribute to building this culture
of experimentation that it costs almost
nothing to do but it's so impactful is
just to ask about experiment results so
I've spoken to folks at organizations
where it is unheard of to launch
something without experiment results and
that's because the product leadership
always asked what did you learn in your
experiment in the in the launch reviews
and so once once it you sort of
established that that precedent and that
expectation that you better come armed
to you better come to these discussions
armed with data then that's how your
that's how your employees start behaving
and so that I think it's yeah start by
generating excitement but you focus on
getting your leadership team on board
and having them adopt the practices that
settings
sample for the for the broader
organization well Pete thank you for
taking the time to come on the show and
talk about a/b testing it's been a great
conversation thank you for having me I
enjoyed it too thanks for listening the
Nessie radio an educational program
brought to you by Triple E software
magazine for more about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at se - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening